<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bruised reed, or, A sermon preach'd at the cathedral church of St. Asaph, for the support of weak Christians by D. Maurice, D.D., sometime chaplain in New Colledge, Oxon.</title>
            <author>Maurice, David.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1357A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43437</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27606281</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27606281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50328)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1728:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bruised reed, or, A sermon preach'd at the cathedral church of St. Asaph, for the support of weak Christians by D. Maurice, D.D., sometime chaplain in New Colledge, Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Maurice, David.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the Theater,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XII, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110142:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BRUISED REED, OR A SERMON Preach'd at the Cathedral Church of St. <hi>ASAPH,</hi> FOR THE <hi>Support of weak Chriſtians,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>D. MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RICE</hi> D. D. ſometime Chaplain in <hi>New Colledge,</hi> OXON.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed at the THEATER, 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:110142:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110142:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 12.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>A bruiſed reed ſhall he not break, and the ſmoking flax ſhall he not quench, 'till he ſend forth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto victory.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF the Scope of this Chapter be ſeriouſly conſider'd, it may be of uſe to Preachers, and Hearers, (a diviſion, which contains all the Members of the Church univerſal, the whole Chriſtian World) for, in the Phariſees here, all Hearers may ſee what is to be avoided, and, in Chriſt, all Preachers may ſee what is to be practis'd, by what is culpable in the one, and commendable in the other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Phariſees entertain hard thoughts of that <hi>great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> of his Church, which was ſent to bring them from Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Light, and from thoſe devious paths of Superſtition, and Errours, which they ran into, unto the way of Life, and Salvation. Secondly, This Prejudice againſt their Teacher was a ſtrong Bolt upon the Doors of their Hearts, that hinder'd them from [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] receiving the Truth in the Love of it. Thirdly, They proceed to blaſpheme Chriſt's Doctrine, and are offended at his Followers, and, from the weakneſs of the Diſciples in <hi>plucking the ears of corn on the Sabbath day,</hi> they take occaſion to oppoſe the Goſpel, as if it were a door open'd by Chriſt to Licentiouſneſs, and Prophaneſs. Fourthly, They have a cloak for their Malice, namely the ſtrict command of obſerving the Sabbath, tho' indeed it was (as Chriſt proves) but their own ſuperſtitious Conceit, and falſe Expoſition of the Command, for the Law allow'd of Works of Neceſſity, ſuch as <hi>plucking the ears of corn</hi> to ſatisfy Hunger, and Works of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſuch as <hi>healing the man with the wither'd hand on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day.</hi> Fifthly, They were obſtinate in their Errours, and would not be convinc'd by him, that was Truth it ſelf, tho'
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110142:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he endeavour'd it by Scripture, Reaſons, and Examples, and thoſe ſo ſtrong, and forcible, that they could not gainſay them. Sixthly, The Prejudice in their Hearts broke out at their Lips, in calling him a <hi>devil,</hi> and their Malice was vented in their Counſels, and Purpoſes, to kill him; ſo that (as all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitours, that I have read on the 31. and 32. <hi>v.</hi> conclude) they ſtop'd not 'till they <hi>ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi> which is the unpardonable Sin ſpoken of there. Therefore let Hearers take heed leſt they give place to the Devil, by entertaining any Prejudices againſt the Perſons, Converſation, or Doctrine, of their Teachers, for that (if cheriſhed) will break out into opprobrious Speeches, and, at laſt, end in a wilfull Oppoſition to the Truth, againſt Knowledge, and Conſcience, and in a bidding defiance to the Almighty. Take heed you ſtand not againſt Convictions, and avoid that <hi>rock of offence,</hi> on which the Phariſees ſuffer'd Shipwrack, but open the windows of your Souls, that the Light of the glorious Goſpel may ſhine in your Hearts, and that you may walk as Children of the Light in your Lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is a Pattern propos'd to Preachers, the grand Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar for us to write after, the LORD JESUS; and that in the Prophecy, and the Hiſtory. Firſt, In ſupporting the weak Diſciples, and defending them againſt the Aſperſions, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of their Adverſaries, as you may read in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Chapter. Secondly, In ſtopping the Mouths of Gain-ſayers with invincible Arguments, drawn from Scripture, Reaſons, Authority, and Examples, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, In Meekneſs, Patience, and Calmneſs of Spirit, withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the hand of Violence, and going where he might do more good, <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fourthly, In Mercyfulneſs, and Tenderneſs to Men's Souls, and Bodies, in Diligence, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, in Preaching and doing good, without any <hi>leaven</hi> of Oſtentation, or vain Glory, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>for he charged them that they ſhould not make him known.</hi> Fifthly, In encouraging, and cheriſhing the leaſt meaſure of Grace, wherever he found it, and uſing all means to bring it to perfection, as in the Text, <hi>A bruiſed reed ſhall he not break,</hi> &amp;c. For there is in the words a <hi>Litote,</hi> where leſs is ſpoken, than is meant, and a double Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110142:3"/>
expreſſing the wonderful Mildneſs, Gentleneſs, and Tenderneſs of Chriſt towards his weak Servants, who are ſo feeble as a Reed, and that bruiſed too, not only toſs'd too and fro, like a Reed, by <hi>every wind of temptation,</hi> but bruiſed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and caſt down, not able to ſtand, or look up towards Heaven, being ſo full of Deadneſs, and Diffidence, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency. Such weak Believers he is ſo far from ſlighting, trampling upon, and laying aſide, (as well he might, as being unprofitable and uſeleſs, for what is a Reed, cruſh'd, and bruis'd good for, unleſs it be for the Fire?) that he will encourage, ſupport, and ſtrengthen, them.</p>
            <p>And, when poor Believers are as <hi>ſmoking flax,</hi> having the leaſt Sparkle of Grace in them, for (as the Proverb is, <hi>there is no ſmoke without ſome fire, tho' it be buried in aſhes</hi>) Chriſt will be ſo far from deſpiſing <hi>the day of ſmall things,</hi> and extinguiſhing this Sparkle, that he will cheriſh, and nouriſh it, and blow it to a Flame, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>donec pronunciet ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quâ ſe victorem declaret omnium inimicorum ſuorum,</hi>] 'Till he pronounces the Sentences, and declares himſelf the Conquerour of his, and their, ſpiritual Enemies, that would really break the <hi>bruiſed reed,</hi> and <hi>quench the ſmoking flax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus ſtrip'd the Text of it's Rhetorical Garments, the Obſervation is naked and plain, and that is this, The Lord Jeſus is very tender of weak Chriſtians, and exceeding care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preſerve the leaſt meaſure of Grace in them. I am not ignorant that ſome take the Words for Chriſt's mercifull deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with troubled Conſciences, and afflicted Souls, that are bruiſed, and cruſhed under the ſenſe of Divine Wrath for Sin, that are full of Doubts, and Fears, touching their everlaſting Condition, without any Candle-light of God's Countenance, and Favour. But I conceive the Metaphor may reach both Senſes, eſpecially the firſt; and methinks the learned Jeſuit <hi>Maldonate</hi> hits the nail on the head, when he ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>Adeo quietè, &amp; attentè ambulabit, ut, etiamſi ſuper arundinem quaſſatam ambulet, tamen non confringet,</hi> He will tread ſo tenderly, ſo warily, ſo gingerly, that, tho' he tread upon a bruiſed Reed, yet it ſhall be no more bruiſed for him.</q> I proceed therefore to handle the point; which I ſhall endeavour to do by ſhewing,
<list>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:110142:4"/>
                  <item>I. What is the leaſt meaſure of Grace;</item>
                  <item>II. That Chriſt is tender of ſuch;</item>
                  <item>III. How he doth ſhew it;</item>
                  <item>IV. The Reaſons why he do's ſo;</item>
                  <item>V. and Laſtly, Apply the whole to our ſelves.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Firſt then I am to ſhew what is that, which we may term the leaſt meaſure of Grace, the <hi>minimum quod non</hi> of Grace, without which a Man cannot, upon Scripture Grounds, be denominated gracious, and having which he may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd that he is <hi>tranſlated from death to life,</hi> and that he is in the ſtate of Grace, a Child of God, a new born Babe of Grace, and an Heir in hope of the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>And truly I find by experience the neceſſity of meditating upon, and handling of, this Subject by us Miniſters, who are often to deal with ſick Perſons on their Death-beds for to adminiſter unto them ſome ſpiritual Phyſick for the health of their Souls. 'Tis the uſual Practice, and Method of our grand Enemy, <hi>the Devil,</hi> to act the part of <hi>Job</hi>'s Wife, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make a Believer to <hi>curſe God</hi> before he dyes, in preſenting him with his Sins in the magnifying, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, Glaſs of the Law, and ſo tempting him to deſpair if he can; at leaſt he will blow out the Candle, that the poor Chriſtian is forced to go to his Bed of Earth in the dark. This Prince of Darkneſs will caſt a miſt between the Chriſtian's Eye of Faith, and the Sun of Righteouſneſs, that he ſhall not be able to ſee the Light of God's Countenance, and then Death muſt needs be a <hi>King of Terrours</hi> to him. Therefore to be well ſatisfy'd in this particular muſt exceedingly encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage a Believer, and infinitely comfort him in that day of Trouble, and Trial, when he is upon the Brink of Eternity, even now entering into thoſe Manſions of Glory, and Satan treading upon his Heel endeavouring to ſend him halting thither, when he cannot ſhut the Door againſt him. This Subject therefore is well worth your Chriſtian Attention, and ſerious Conſideration. Yet before I proceed to my firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, I muſt neceſſarily premiſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is very difficult for any one to diſcern in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf whether he has the leaſt meaſure of Grace, whether he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110142:4"/>
be this <hi>bruiſed reed</hi> or no? tho' in it ſelf it is eaſily diſcernable, and therefore the School-men diſtinguiſh betwixt Grace <hi>in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ ſuâ</hi> and Grace <hi>in perſonâ gratiosâ,</hi> Grace <hi>in Ideâ,</hi> and Grace <hi>in ſubjecto;</hi> in it's own Nature 'tis eaſy to know it by plain Scripture Rules, and Signs, but, in the gracious Perſon, 'tis hard for him, by a reflex act of Faith, to perceive it, for theſe Reaſons. Firſt, as there is [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] a damnable ſelf Love, and ſelf Conceit, in the ungodly, ſo is there a ſelf Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in the Godly; the one is blown up with a falſe, ill grounded, Hope, and the other is kept down by a weak Faith; 'tis therefore equally difficult to make the one believe he has Grace, as the other to believe he has none: for ſo indeed the Scripture deſcribes them; the true Believer is <hi>poor in ſpirit,</hi> low, and vile, in his own Eyes, the <hi>greateſt of ſinners,</hi> and the leaſt of all Saints, and therefore <hi>he hungers and thirſts after Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> in a deep ſenſe of the want of it; the other is of a <hi>Laodicean</hi> temper, <hi>lukewarm</hi> in his Devotions, careleſs in his Profeſſion, being <hi>rich,</hi> and full, and ſeeing <hi>no need of any thing,</hi> when indeed he wants all things, his Riches are but Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Lord <hi>will ſend him empty away;</hi> ſo we find the proud hypocritical Phariſee blown up (like the Toad in the Fable) with the wind of ſelf applauſe, lifting himſelf above his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by his odious Compariſons, when the poor humble Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, by a ſerious Reflection on the Infirmity of his Nature, had not ſo much Confidence as to <hi>look up.</hi> Secondly, 'Tis hard to diſcern the leaſt meaſure of Grace, becauſe falſe Grace ſo nearly reſembles it. There has been a great deal of ſtir kept in the late times about common Grace, and ſpecial Grace, true Grace, and counterfeit, whether they differ'd gradually, or ſpecifically, and, if they differ'd ſpecifically, whether mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, or phyſically; and many ſuch Diſtinctions, and Notions, I think, to little purpoſe; at laſt it was concluded, (by the Combatants) that there was a ſpecifical moral Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, as between Vertue, and Vice, as Vertue and Vice do differ gradually, and yet ſpecifically too, as for example, the exceſſive degree of Liberality, which is a Vertue, is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality, which is a Vice. But, however they differ in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it is certain from Scripture, and Examples, that the true
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110142:5"/>
Believer, eſpecially the weak Believer, and the Hypocrite, do differ very little; yea many times the Hypocrite exceeds the truly pious in outward appearance, which will appear if we conſider the Repentance of <hi>Ahab,</hi> the Zeal of <hi>Jehu,</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> that were in the Hearers compar'd to the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> and how <hi>Herod heard John the Baptiſt gladly, and did many things,</hi> and there was but one thing lacking in the young Man in the Goſpel, to wit his ſecret Sin of Covetouſneſs, which was the only <hi>Remora,</hi> that kept him from Chriſt; and ſo blameleſs was the outward Converſation of <hi>Judas</hi> among the Diſciples, that each of them might ſuſpect himſelf to be the Traitor, as well as he. This makes many a poor Chriſtian to <hi>work out his ſalvation with fear, and trembling,</hi> and to endeavour to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run the moſt refin'd Hypocrite <hi>in the race that is ſet before him:</hi> and this makes the leaſt meaſure of Grace ſo imperceptible by us. 'Tis the Lord Jeſus alone, that has the <hi>fan in his hand, who will throughly purge his floor,</hi> and ſeparate the <hi>wheat</hi> from the <hi>chaff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing to be premiſed is, that, wherever the leaſt meaſure of Grace is, there will be a longing deſire, and an earneſt endeavour after more Grace, and a conſtant uſe of the means appointed for the obtaining of it. But the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Profeſſor is contented, if he can keep up a more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Profeſſion, and an external Conformity, ſo far, as to keep up his Reputation among Men, and he cares for no more. If he knew how much Grace would bring him once within the Precincts of Heaven, he would never look after one degree of Grace more. But the truly gracious, like St. <hi>Paul, forgets the things, that are behind, and reacheth forward to the things,</hi> that are before, <hi>and ſtill preſſeth toward the mark, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3.13, 14. he is as eager for the obtaining of that Perfection of Grace, which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, the Reſurrection from the dead, as he was in perſecuting the Church, wherein he confeſſeth he <hi>was mad,</hi> and enrag'd with a furious blind Zeal, for he expreſſeth both by the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.11. compar'd with <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>And that is the reaſon why the Acts, and Exerciſe of Grace are expreſs'd, in Scripture, in terms of Indigency, and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110142:5"/>
ſuch as <hi>poverty, hunger, thirſt, panting, breathing, running, wreſtling, preſſing forward, following hard after, ſtriving, earneſt ſeeking, fighting, reſiſting even to blood,</hi> &amp;c. Oh, ſays the true Believer, that I had communion with God, and a ſenſe of his Favour, and the light of his Countenance upon me! for that would be better than Life. Oh! had I an Intereſt in Chriſt, and the aſſurance of it, and I ſhould never grieve more; oh! could I obtain a mortifying, ſtrengthening, Grace, and a dead blow to every Luſt, 'twere enough. This is the Chriſtian's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in every Ordinance. Theſe things, premis'd, I now come to my firſt Propoſal, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew what is the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace: this I ſhall do by conſidering two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. What Infirmities they are, which do not neceſſarily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it, or with which it may be conſiſtent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. (To come nearer to our purpoſe) What are it's Effects, without which there can be no meaſure of Grace.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, thoſe Infirmities are chiefly three,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The leaſt meaſure of Grace may conſiſt with a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Ignorance, for the beſt and ſtrongeſt do know <hi>but in part,</hi> and the great Doctor of the Gentiles includes himſelf in the number 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 12. And Chriſt's own Diſciples were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the very fundamental Principles of Religion, ſuch as the <hi>Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> 'till they ſaw it with their Eyes, in Chriſt's Reſurrection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may conſiſt with a great many Doubts, and Fears touching our everlaſting Condition; for the aſſurance of Faith is a Love-token, which Chriſt ſends from Heaven, but to very few, ſtrong, well-grown Chriſtians; leſt it ſhould be abus'd to Licentiouſneſs, Slothfulneſs, and carnal Security; and as much as is wanting of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22.) full aſſurance of Faith, ſo much of Doubts and Fears are there in the Soul; as it is in hot Water, whatever is ſhort of the extream Degrees of Heat, there are ſo many Degrees of Cold in it, ſo it is for Faith, and Doubts. Tho' Faith indeed, as 'tis conſider'd objectively for an Act of the Soul laying hold on Chriſt, admits of no Degrees, but conſider'd as an Habit infus'd, it increaſeth or diminiſheth according to the Believer's Care, and Induſtry: yea 'tis no hard matter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110142:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to prove that <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, <hi>the father of the faithful,</hi> did very much falter in his Faith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.4. The Lord made him a promiſe of <hi>ſeed by Sarah,</hi> and yet, out of Diffidence of God's Promiſe, he went in <hi>unto his maid;</hi> elſe certainly, had his Faith been exercis'd, he might ſoon have ſilenc'd <hi>Sarah,</hi> when ſhe made the motion in <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Behold now the Lord reſtrained me from bearing, I pray thee go in unto my maid.</hi> And in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.18. he diſcovers the weakneſs of his Faith again; for, when God had told him he would <hi>give</hi> him <hi>a ſon by Sarah, v.</hi> 16. he prays for <hi>Iſhmael</hi> there; and that this proceeded from the weakneſs of his Faith appears clearly from the Lord's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that Prayer, <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>And God ſaid Sarah thy wife ſhall bear thee a ſon indeed, and thou ſhalt call his name Iſaac,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Why doſt thou doubt of my Promiſe, and misbelieve my Word, and, out of that diffidence of a Child <hi>by Sarah,</hi> doſt thou pray for <hi>Iſhmael?</hi> I tell thee again thou ſhalt have a Son by <hi>Sarah,</hi> and that indeed, and of a truth. And how often doth Chriſt upbraid his Diſciples with this? <hi>O ye of little faith;</hi> and where there is but little Faith, there is much Doubtings, but none dare deny they had Grace, therefore the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace is conſiſtent with much Doubtings and Fears.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There may be the leaſt meaſure of Grace where there are many, and ſtrong, Corruptions, as we read of <hi>Rahab, Sampſon,</hi> and others, that were guilty of repeating the ſame Sins, and thoſe of the firſt magnitude, and yet we ſee them reckon'd among the Faithful, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 'Tis true the leaſt meaſure of true Grace diſpoſſeth the old Man of the Heart, that Sin ſhall not ſit on the Throne there any more, the Believer is not the Servant of Sin, nor allows the leaſt Sin in himſelf. In the ungracious Perſon, Sin, and Satan, rule the roſt, and all is quiet, but, <hi>when a ſtronger than he comes,</hi> to wit the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, he is diſpoſſeſs'd, and ſo 'tis no longer Satan's Houſe, he loſeth his Title, and Sin is but an Uſurper, tho' it remains there, and thence comes the laſting Combat betwixt Fleſh, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, having their Viciſſitudes of Prevalency over each other. This made an eminent Champion in Chriſtianity complain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19. <hi>For the good, that I would, I do not, but the evil which I would not, that I do:</hi> how much more prevalent are Luſts in a weak Chriſtian!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:110142:6"/>But Secondly, As to it's Effects, they are again chiefly three: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Where there is a meaſure of Grace, there is a filial Fear of God; which, when ſtrong Temptations are ready to prevail, will come in to the Soul's reſcue, and make a Believer to ſay with <hi>Joſeph, How ſhall I do this great evil and Sin againſt God?</hi> againſt that good God, that hath done me good, and not evil, all my days? againſt a holy and juſt God, which cannot abide Iniquity, and will render unto me, and <hi>to every one according to</hi> our <hi>works?</hi> againſt an all-ſeeing God, that ſee'th in ſecret, and rewardeth openly? And, as this Fear for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifys the Soul againſt preſumptuous Sins, ſo it ſpurs the Soul on to <hi>run the ways of God's commandments;</hi> and therefore it is coupled with the keeping of God's Commands, as the cauſe, and the effect, as the means, and the end, <hi>fear God, that thou may'ſt keep his commandments:</hi> This <hi>fear of the Lord is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſdom,</hi> it is the <hi>primum vivens,</hi> and <hi>ultimum moriens,</hi> the very heart of the new Creature, for, as ſoon as ever ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life is breath'd into the Soul, this Fear and Awe of God mingles it ſelf with all the Thoughts, Words, and Actions; and this Fear too lays the Top-ſtone in the ſpiritual Building, <hi>for</hi> we are to <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Where there is a meaſure of Grace, there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to fear God, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Lord hear the prayers of thy ſervants, that deſire to fear thy name;</hi> they could not ſay they fear'd his name, but might boldly ſay they deſir'd it. And, as it is in Sin, a Deſire, tho' it proceeds no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a Sin, ſo gracious Deſires are accepted of God, and the will to do good is taken for the deed. As Heart-adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and Heart-murther, (tho' terminated in the Will, yet) are great Sins in the ſight of God, ſo are the gracious Ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and holy Breathings of the Soul, as precious in his ſight, as the other are odious. But, leſt any ſhould turn this Grace of God into Wantonneſs, you muſt conſider that this Deſire has it's Concomitants, and Properties to attend it, which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth it from the cold, lazy Velleities of the ungodly, for it is, Firſt, a ſerious, hearty Deſire, Secondly, a laſting, growing Deſire, Thirdly, it is mingled with Sorrow, that it can go no farther, Fourthly, it is attended with a Reſtleſsneſs 'till it can
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110142:7"/>
proceed to act, Fifthly, it drives the Believer therefore often on his Knees to beg Strength to do, as well as to will, Sixthly, it is ſuch as is oppos'd, and reſiſted by Temptations, that would quench it, this is the <hi>ſmoking flax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. and Laſtly, Where there is a meaſure of Grace, there is a real Love to the Children of God, as ſuch; if you love God's Image of Holineſs wherever you meet with it, in the poor, as well as in the rich, it is a ſign that you are tranſlated from Darkneſs to Light, and <hi>from death to life,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Second thing propos'd is to ſhew, That the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is tender, and careful of thoſe that have this ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace, and this will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From his many Promiſes to ſuch, which are his own Hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and the weakeſt Chriſtians may plead them, and, with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Boldneſs, preſs God to perform them, <hi>for he is faithful who hath promis'd.</hi> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.11. there is a Prophecy of Chriſt, where he is compar'd to a Shepherd, <hi>he ſhall feed his flock like a Shepherd,</hi> he ſhall gather his Lambs with his Arm, and carry them in his Boſome, and ſhall gently lead thoſe, that are with young, and <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>He giveth power to the faint, and to them, who have no might he increaſeth ſtrength.</hi> Here are moſt pregnant Promiſes of Chriſt's Care toward weak Believers, they have his Arms to defend them, and his Boſome to nouriſh them, his Hands to provide for them, and his Heart to love them, and, leſt they ſhould doubt of this (as they are apt to do) he farther preſſeth his Truth, and Power, his Faithfulneſs, and Goodneſs, to all that wait on him, but eſpecially the weak, and wearied, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29, 31. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72.12, 13, 14. <hi>David</hi> prays for his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> and, from a Prieſt, turns Prophet, in foretelling the Happineſs of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Reign, as the Type, and of Chriſt, as the Antitype, the one for temporal, the other for ſpiritual. <hi>He ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the needy, when he cryeth, the poor, and him that hath no helper. He ſhall ſpare the poor, and needy, and ſhall ſave the Souls of the needy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Lord, thou haſt heard the deſire of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thou wilt prepare their heart, and cauſe thine ear to hear.</hi> This Promiſe is to ſuch weak humble Chriſtians, that have not Heart to pray; the Lord will prepare their Hearts, and fill
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110142:7"/>
their Mouths; ſo <hi>Ez.</hi> 34.16. <hi>I will ſeek that, which was loſt, and bring again that, which was driven away, and will bind up that, which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that, which was ſick:</hi> and to theſe belong all the Promiſes that are made to the <hi>poor in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the hungry,</hi> and <hi>thirſty,</hi> the <hi>weary</hi> and <hi>heavy laden,</hi> for, as the ſenſe of the want of Grace is Grace, ſo theſe Promiſes of Peace, Comfort, and eternal Happyneſs are intayl'd upon it, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.53. <hi>John</hi> 7.47. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28, 29. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 44.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This appears from the ſtrict Charge he gives his Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and Deputies, on Earth, to wit, Magiſtrates, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, to take care of them, and be tender of them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.22, 23. He commands <hi>Kings to be their nurſing fathers,</hi> and <hi>Queens to be their nurſing mothers.</hi> It was in his own Commiſſion at firſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, 2. and he would have his Meſſengers, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, that ſpeak in his Name to do the like, to wit, <hi>to bring glad tidings to the meek, to heal the broken hearted, and to comfort them that mourn.</hi> The only way that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was to manifeſt his Love to Chriſt, and make ſome amends for his ſhameful Denial of him, was by his <hi>feeding his lambs, John</hi> 21.5. and who are thoſe, but young, and weak Chriſtians, not in reſpect of Age, and Stature in Body, but in reſpect of Growth, and Strength in Grace, and the double charge he gave him calls for his double Care.</p>
            <p>So he commands his Church in <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. to be careful of his <hi>Kids,</hi> and <hi>feed</hi> them <hi>beſide the Shepherd's tents,</hi> and take heed leſt they <hi>turn aſide by the flock of his companions,</hi> that is, be ſeduced by falſe Apoſtles, who pretended to be his Companions, and Friends, but indeed were his real Enemies, <hi>wolves in ſheeps cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Zech. 4.10. He expoſtulates with the People there, and clears himſelf, ſaying, <hi>who hath deſpis'd the day of ſmall things?</hi> Not I, neither would I have any other deſpiſe that Temple, which was a Type of the Church of Chriſt, and of every Member of it: It was not ſo glorious as the Firſt Temple, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the People, that had ſeen the firſt, wept, when they ſaw this, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.3. But the Lord would not deſpiſe it.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third Particular is to ſhew how Chriſt doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110142:8"/>
this Care, and Tenderneſs towards weak Chriſtians, this he doth, Firſt, By preſerving them from ſtrong Temptations, that are too heavy for them to bear, which well-grown Chriſtians might undergo; an inſtance whereof we have in St. <hi>Peter, Jo.</hi> 21.18. <hi>When he was young,</hi> he had his liberty to go <hi>whither he would,</hi> becauſe his weakneſs in Faith could not endure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and hardſhip, but, when he became an old, grown, ſtrong, Believer, he ſhould be led in Chains <hi>whither he would not,</hi> for then his ſtrength could bear it: when he could reckon his ſhackles of Iron, as great Ornaments, as Chains of Gold, and Glory in Tribulation for the ſake of Chriſt, then ſhould he be loaded with them, and no ſooner.</p>
            <p>But more particularly he exerciſeth his very tender care of their Weakneſs, 1. In not impoſing ſuch hard ſervice upon them, as on other of a greater ſtanding in Chriſtianity, as we ſee clearly in Chriſt's tenderneſs of his weak Diſciples, he grants them an Immunity from the ſeverer duties of <hi>faſting,</hi> and <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> when the Baptiſt's Diſciples charg'd them with the neglect thereof, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.14. Chriſt makes an Apology for them, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16, 17. by comparing their Weakneſs to <hi>old bottles,</hi> that were not fit, nor able, to hold ſtrong <hi>new</hi> Liquors, and to <hi>old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that were inconſiſtent with <hi>new cloth,</hi> becauſe ſubject to Rents, and Breaches; and ſo were they to Temptations, and Diſcouragements, if put upon ſuch hard ſervices, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with ſuch unwelcome duties upon the very threſhold of their Profeſſion, their entrance into Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>So doth he indulge their Weakneſs in <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.40, 41. <hi>What could ye not watch with me one hour?</hi> methinks the ſhortneſs of the time might leſſen the difficulty of the duty, and yet they were ſo overcome with Sleep, that they could <hi>not watch one hour;</hi> but, for all that, inſtead of ſharply reproving them for their Sloth, he puts an excuſe into their mouths, <hi>The Spirit indeed is willing, but the fleſh is weak.</hi> So mercifull is our high Prieſt, that, where the ability is wanting, he'll accept the will for the deed. And this was the reaſon that he was ſo indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the Catechumeni, we read of in the Goſpel, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.1, 2, 3. His Bowels yearn'd within him for Pity, (as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies) becauſe they were <hi>come from far,</hi> and, if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110142:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
diſmiſs'd them without Meat, they were in danger of <hi>fainting by the way,</hi> and ſo might be deferr'd from ſuch an unwelcome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that was ſo diſpleaſing to Fleſh and Blood; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, leſt thoſe young Goſpellers ſhould be diſcourag'd, he puts his Divinity on work to feed them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As he will not impoſe upon them hard ſervices, ſo he will not expoſe them to great ſufferings. They need not ſuch <hi>thorns in the fleſh</hi> to keep them low, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had after his high Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and Revelations. <hi>If ye ſeek me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Jo.</hi> 18.1. <hi>let theſe go their way,</hi> that is, theſe are yet unfit to aſcend the ſtage of ſufferings, they are not able to act the Tragedy, which I muſt under your bloody hands; therefore <hi>let theſe go their way</hi> excus'd; and ſuitable to this care, and tenderneſs, is his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>He will not ſuffer us to be tempted above that we are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape.</hi> He is cloth'd with the ſame Fleſh, and Blood, as we are, (ſin only excepted) and therefore he knows what Mould we are made of, and ſo will proportion our burthen to our backs.</p>
            <p>Here, by the way, I might anſwer the objection of an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Believer, who doubts of his intereſt in Chriſt from, or by reaſon of, his heavy Preſſures, and ſays with <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> If it be ſo, why am I thus? If I be a child of God, why do I feel a Hell in my Soul? as if I were in Hell already; if my Soul be bound up in the bundle of Life, why am I become a prey to the roaring Lyon? as appears by his continual buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting of me; but (O believing Soul!) thou ſhould'ſt from thence argue the contrary, and conclude (for thy comfort) from theſe ſtrong ſtruglings in thy Soul, that there are two Nations within thee, ſuch as they in <hi>Rebeccah</hi>'s Womb, the one from Heaven, heavenly, the other from Earth, earthly, and be ſure that at laſt the <hi>elder ſhall ſerve the younger,</hi> Nature ſhall be ſubdu'd by Grace; and therefore thou may'ſt argue, from the weight of thy afflictions, that thou art not only a true Believer, but a ſtrong Believer, whom God loads ſo heavily, for he will lay upon none but what they are able to bear.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He preſerves them from ſtrong Temptations by praying for them, that they may be able to bear them, and that the <hi>bruiſed reed</hi> may never be a <hi>broken reed,</hi> and the <hi>ſmoking flax be never
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110142:9"/>
quenched;</hi> this is the drift of Chriſt's Prayer for his Diſciples in <hi>Jo.</hi> 17. and not for them only, but for all Babes in Chriſt, that ſhall be born to him to the end of the World, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.20. So Chriſt prays for St. <hi>Peter, when Satan would have winnowed him, Luke</hi> 22.31. The poyſonous breath of that ſubtle Serpent had ſoon fann'd away this weak Diſciple from Chriſt's Floor, if Chriſt had not ſuddenly interpos'd by his Interceſſion, and ſo do's he ſtill continue his prevailing <hi>interceſſion in Heaven</hi> for his weak Members, that they ſhall never miſcarry as long as he is at God's right hand to mediate for them; and thus he preſerves them from ſtrong Temptations by not impoſing hard ſervices on them, nor expoſing them to great ſufferings, and by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He manifeſts his tender care of weak Believers by ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their Weakneſs to them, that their failings ſhall be their Advantages, and that they may be gainers by their loſſes. St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood too firm on his own legs, he was too confident of his own ſtrength, when he tells Chriſt, that, <hi>tho' all ſhould forſake him, yet would not he,</hi> and yet he was the firſt that did it, becauſe he lean'd too much on his own ſtaff, which prov'd to him but a broken Reed. He had not yet (it ſeems) learn'd that great, and hard leſſon of SELF-DENIAL; for, if he had learn'd to deny himſelf, he would never had deny'd his Maſter, as he did moſt ſhamefully three times.</p>
            <p>Therefore doth Chriſt force him to a triple Confeſſion of his Faith in him, and Love to him, <hi>Jo.</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. <hi>Loveſt thou me more than theſe?</hi> where by his modeſt anſwer you may obſerve the ſelf Diffidence, and Humility, which he gain'd by his Fall, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> There is now no ſelf-exaltation above others, he doth not ſay now, tho' all ſhould hate thee, yet I will love thee, and cleave to thee; no, but he referrs himſelf to Chriſt's all-ſeeing eye, who ſaw more by him, than he could know by himſelf; and therefore he would ſay nothing, leſt he ſhould judge amiſs; ſo humble, ſo low, ſo vile, was he become in his own eyes. Thus when a poor Chriſtian is ſenſible of his own Weakneſs, and finds thoſe ſons of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> his Luſts, to be too ſtrong for him, and therefore fears, like <hi>David,</hi> to fall one day into their hands; then doth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110142:9"/>
he become a dayly petitioner to the great God for ſtrength, he prays more feelingly, more fervently, and will not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd; and this is his ſtrength; ſo <hi>Jacob's</hi> wreſtling with God is call'd <hi>his ſtrength,</hi> Hoſ. 12.3.</p>
            <p>When he ſees how ſlovenly he is in every work, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which God calls him to, how he bungles in his holieſt performances, and has greater reaſons, than the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. to ſay, <hi>To will is preſent with me, but how to perform that, which is good, I find not,</hi> he is filled with ſelf-abhorrence, humility, and <hi>poverty of ſpirit,</hi> which are precious graces in the ſight of God. Whereas naturally we take a pride in our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, and thoſe duties, which grow upon Nature's ſtock, do fill the hypocritical Profeſſor with a vain conceit of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and makes him reſt in <hi>[opere operato]</hi> the work done: but, on the other ſide, a true Believer, out of ſelf-diffidence, runs out of himſelf to Chriſt, he dares not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſtay under the roof of his own works, or duties, but comes up, like the Spouſe in the Canticles, from a wilderneſs of temptation, leaning on his beloved Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo continually, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> magnifies God's ſuperabundant Grace towards him, for elſe he is in himſelf but a firebrand of Hell, undone for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He manifeſts this tenderneſs, and care towards weak Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, by ſending them help in a time of need, in relieving them at a dead lift: when this ſparkle is even extinguiſh'd, then will the Lord wonderfully ſtep in, many times, to help, as he promiſeth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>a help in a good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</hi> The temporal deliverance, which the Jews had from the <hi>Aſsyrians, Iſaiah</hi> 37. was a type, and a figure, of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deliverance, which the Lord gives this <hi>bruiſed reed,</hi> when it is ready to break, when the new Creature is ready to give up the Ghoſt: the City <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was as <hi>a woman in travel, the children were come to the birth, but there was no ſtrength to bring forth;</hi> (a miſerable ſtreight!) Then came one of Heaven's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties as a skilfull Midwife to give them ſpeedy deliverance.</p>
            <p>Many are the experiences of the Servants of God of his Providence towards them, in reſcuing them from the very Jaws
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110142:10"/>
of the <hi>roaring Lyon,</hi> when he was ready to <hi>devour them,</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming them by ſome ſeaſonable Providence, when they were ready to commit ſome horrid abomination, that would have diſhonour'd God, and made his enemies to blaſpheme, and have wounded their Profeſſion, their Conſciences, and good Names for ever; a paſſage to this purpoſe I have read in the Life of a reverend and godly Divine of this Kingdom, which is ſo remarkable, that I cannot omit it; <q>This reverend Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, being at his houſe very late in a winter night, ready to go to his reſt, when all his Family were aſleep, a ſudden thought took him, that he muſt go to ſuch a Man's houſe, that liv'd a pretty diſtance from him; at firſt he ſtrugled againſt thoſe motions, and endeavour'd to ſtifle them, as being unreaſonable, enthuſiaſtical impreſſions, that ſhould move him to go to ſuch a houſe without any occaſion apparent to him, and that in an unſeaſonable time of the night (and, for ought he knew, the ſuggeſtions might be ſatanical) But he could have no reſt in his Spirit 'till he took a Candle, and Lantern, and went, and ſo knock'd at the Man's door a while before any Body anſwer'd, at length the Man of the houſe comes, and opens the door; This Miniſter told him of the ſtrange, and ſtrong, impulſe, that mov'd him to come thither, and that he had no buſineſs; <hi>Nay then,</hi> ſays the poor Man with tears in his eyes, <hi>I ſee the wonderful mercy of God in ſending you hither to reſcue my Soul, and Body, from the Devil; for juſt now was I (when I had got all my houſhold to their reſt) fully purpoſing, with this cord, to diſpatch my ſelf away, and now, bleſsed be God for his gracious providence, in preventing it by your coming</hi>
               </q>. Here was a ſeaſonable help; when the <hi>ſmoking flax</hi> was even quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Lord ſtept in wonderfully with relief: ſo careful and tender is he of the weakeſt Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By preſerving them from falſe Teachers, and Seducers, 'till they have their ſenſes to diſcern between Good, and Evil, between Truth, and Falſhood; therefore a ſtrict charge is given by him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Take us the foxes, the little foxes, that ſpoil the vines, for our vines have tender grapes;</hi> eſpecially care is to be had of weak Believers, which are as <hi>tender grapes,</hi> leſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110142:10"/>
               <hi>the foxes,</hi> and <hi>little foxes,</hi> that is, Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, ſeduce them; and here St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves touching the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouns US and OUR, <hi>Poterat dicere capite [mihi,] ſed maluit dicere [nobis,] conſortio delectatus,</hi> and he ſo unites our welfare with his own, that he takes as great care of us, as of himſelf, and of the whole Church together, and every particular Member thereof, from the greateſt to the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Fourth Particular to be conſider'd in the handling of this Text, is to ſhew the Reaſons why Chriſt is ſo tender of weak Chriſtians, and thoſe are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Grace may be hinder'd in it's Growth by ſuch things as the Believer cannot prevent, as for inſtance, A Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever may be living in a wicked Family, where there is no fear of God, and there he has much ado to keep his Sparkle alive, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.13. The Lord takes notice of that <hi>little good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that was in <hi>Abijah in the houſe of Jeroboam,</hi> a little Grace in ſuch a Family went far. Even ſo doth the Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that ſmall meaſure of Piety, that was in <hi>Lot;</hi> which ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was but a Sparkle in a ſea of Corruption, as we may ſee by tracing his Converſation; for firſt, out of a ſinful fear of the filthy <hi>Sodomites,</hi> he proffers them his two Daughters for to commit Uncleanneſs with them; his Drunkenneſs, and Inceſt, recorded in Scriptures, are as a <hi>Scylla,</hi> and <hi>Charybdis</hi> for all Chriſtians to beware, and fear to come near them; the latter being ſuch a ſin, as the Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. as is not ſo much as nam d among the unbelieving Gentiles, much leſs practis'd by them: and one would think that the commiſſion of one ſuch ſin of Inceſt might terrify the weakeſt Believer in the World, that had any fear of God before his eyes, from ever committing the like again, and not only ſo, but would make him go mourning all his days; but we find that the ſin of Drunkenneſs, that opens every door in the Soul to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemy, lets in this abomination again, and that ſuddenly too, for the next night he lay with his other Daughter; from both which inceſtuous mixtures proceeded the curſed Brood of <hi>Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Ammonites,</hi> that were the greateſt ſcourge of the people of God in all the World, yet, for all theſe groſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110142:11"/>
carriages, and great ſins, he was ſtill a <hi>ſmoking flax,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in mercy paſſeth by his enormities, and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the place of his abode, gives him a grain of allowance for being ſo good among a people ſo bad, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. He has the Epithets of <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> and <hi>godly, becauſe he was vex'd</hi> that they were ſo ungodly. So doth the Lord exerciſe the ſame indulgence towards <hi>the Church of Pergamus,</hi> becauſe ſhe dwelt in the very confines of Hell, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. <hi>I know thy works, and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satan's ſeat is;</hi> and where was that? where Godlineſs was perſecuted, and Idolatry was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd, together with the community of Wives maintain'd, which was the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans.</hi> Now to hold faſt the Chriſtian Profeſſion, and not to deny the Faith in the Devil's quarters, was an Argument of a Heaven-born Nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will diſpenſe with other Weakneſſes.</p>
            <p>Only, when a Chriſtian's lot is caſt into ſuch a wicked place, where Satan dwelleth either for falſe Doctrine, and Worſhip, or Sodomitical Practices, 'tis his duty to bewail it with the Prophet <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 120.5, 6. <hi>Wo is me that I ſojourn in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar, my Soul hath long dwelt with him, that hateth peace;</hi> he longed to be away from them: and ſo did the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> mourn, becauſe he <hi>dwelt among a people of unclean lips,</hi> Iſa. 6.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grace may be hinder'd in it's growth by reaſon of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's conſtitution of Body, for the philoſophical Axiom holds true in Grace, as it doth in Morality, <hi>mores animi ſequuntur temperamentum corporis;</hi> for we find cholerick Bodys very apt to fall into immoderate Anger, and unbridled Paſſion, upon the leaſt provocation, and are often to ſeek for that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Grace of Patience: and thoſe, that are phlegmatick, are not ſo active, and zealous, in the ſervice of God, as others, that are but of an equal ſtature in Grace; ſo the melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick cannot rejoyce in God, and be ſo chearful in holy duties, as others; and thoſe, that are ſanguine, cannot be ſo ſerious; and the weak crazy Bodies cannot ſpend ſo much time, and ſtrength in Watching, Faſting, and Prayer, as thoſe, that are of a ſtronger conſtitution, for, without controverſy, tho' Grace
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110142:11"/>
do's not depend upon the temper of the Body <hi>[quoad eſſe &amp; cauſam]</hi> in it's eſſence and cauſe, yet it do's <hi>[quoad eſſe &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citium]</hi> as to it's well being, and exerciſe, and therefore the Lord will not <hi>quench the ſmoking flax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Grace may be hinder'd in it's growth by reaſon of weak gifts, and want of natural parts, ſuch as Memory to carry away the word, read, or heard, and the gift of Prayer. A Sigh from ſuch is acceptable to God, for God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the <hi>Logick,</hi> nor <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> nor <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> but the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, of Prayer: 'tis the ſincere broken petitions, that flow from a broken heart, that prevail with God more, than all the gaudy Eloquence of any Hypocrite whatever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Chriſtian's Grace may be weak for want of the means of Grace, many people have been unfruitful under, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull for, the word of God, and therefore the Lord may in Judgement ſay of them what <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Let there be no dew, neither let there be rain upon you:</hi> (A dreadful curſe!) And, if a weak Chriſtian chance to be in ſuch a barren Wilderneſs, the Lord will bear with his <hi>bruiſed reed,</hi> becauſe he has not the means of growth, and ſtrength, to wit, <hi>the milk,</hi> and ſtrong meat, of the word. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom much is given, much ſhall be required,</hi> that is, he, that has been planted by the rivers of waters, and enjoyed powerfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and plentiful means of Grace, the Lord do's expect from ſuch, an anſwerable growth in Grace, and Knowledge; and ſo without queſtion, he doth from you all, that do frequent this Church; but, if a poor Chriſtian's lot has fall'n upon a mount <hi>Gilboa,</hi> the Lord will not expect ſo much from him, but will conſider ſuch weaklings in Grace, that are ſo for want of ſpiritual Food, and bear with their weakneſſes.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt reaſon why our Saviour is ſo tender of weak Chriſtians, and very careful to preſerve the leaſt meaſure of Grace in them, to wit, becauſe Grace may be hinder'd in it's growth by ſuch things as the Believer cannot prevent, and thoſe are, firſt, A Believer may be living in a wicked Family, as <hi>Abijah</hi> was, ſecondly, It may ariſe from the temper of the Believer's Body, thirdly, from the weakneſs of his natural
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110142:12"/>
Parts, fourthly from the want of means of Grace, as thoſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. <hi>that knew not whether there was a ſpirit or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon why Chriſt is ſo tender, is, becauſe he is the Purchaſer of the leaſt meaſure of Grace: this <hi>ſmoking flax</hi> is the price of Chriſt's Blood; and what coſt him ſo dear ſhall never be loſt by his good will: and the ſame good will, that he had to ſpend his Heart's Blood to redeem them, will ſurely ingage his almighty Power to defend them. This adds weight to the charge of the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves, and to all the flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers, to feed the Church of God,</hi> which he hath purchas'd with his own Blood; as if he ſhould ſay, the meaneſt among you is of an ineſtimable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, no leſs, than the price of God's own Blood, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee you have an eſpecial care of them. And, if he lays ſo great a charge on his Miniſters to look to them, ſurely he will not forget them himſelf, but will make it his conſtant bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in Heaven <hi>to intercede for them,</hi> that none ſhall pluck them out of his hands, whom he paid ſo dear for.</p>
            <p>He, that was made a Prieſt by God's oath to ſacrifice his own Life, to redeem ſinners from Death, <hi>continues for ever a prieſt to intercede for,</hi> and procure them, the full price of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, to wit Grace, and Glory: and this exceeding great care he takes for weak Believers appear'd preſently after his aſcenſion into Heaven by the ſpeedy diſpatch he made of his Spirit to the ſupply of the weak Orphans at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> (for ſo the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples were, 'till he ſent the Comforter unto them, and ſo he calls them, <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) &amp; the <hi>Comforter</hi> he ſent, to wit the Holy Spirit, aſſoon as he was warm (if I may ſo ſpeak) in his ſeat in Heaven, at God's right hand, to the unſpeakable comfort of them, and us, and all Believers to the end of the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reaſon is, becauſe this Holy Spirit is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the leaſt meaſure of Grace, and therefore will not leave his work unfiniſh'd, or neglect what he hath ſo graciouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, but, <hi>having begotten us again unto a lively hope,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3, 5. <hi>he will keep us by his mighty power through faith unto ſalvation.</hi> If all the created powers of Heaven, and Earth, were united, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110142:12"/>
concentred, in one perſon, yet he could not ſo much as make this Flax to ſmoke, 'tis the effect of Divine power, Grace is the product of the Spirit, <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.5. and therefore, ſince the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit is the Father of ſuch gracious diſpenſations, he'll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the ſame ſtrength to preſerve what he hath begot: <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18, 19, 20. We ſee how ſoon doth the Lord hear <hi>Ephraim</hi> bemoaning himſelf, when he was as a <hi>ſmoking flax,</hi> a newly <hi>tamed heifer</hi> brought to God under the yoke of Afflictions; his cry ſoon pierceth God's ears, and his ear affects his bowels, and his bowels awake his power to be his guardian.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt brings a wandring ſheep into his fold, he <hi>puts it on his ſhoulder,</hi> and <hi>rejoyceth</hi> all the way he brings it home, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.5. The power of his Spirit is that ſhoulder, on which he carries it, the everlaſting arms, wherein he bears his lambs, and thoſe <hi>eagle's wings,</hi> upon which they are both tenderly, and ſecurely, convey'd to glory, <hi>Ex.</hi> 19.4. nay he uſeth more care, and tenderneſs, towards weak Believers, than the ſtrong, becauſe of their weakneſs, for the weakeſt child can call God <hi>father,</hi> and the more weak, and feeble, the child is, the greater is the care, and ſtricter is the eye, and obſervance of the mother upon him, what <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>Job</hi> 31.15. the weakeſt, and moſt faint, Believer may ſay the ſame of the ſtrongeſt champion in the Lord's houſe, <hi>did not one, and the ſame holy Spirit faſhion us in the womb?</hi> and if they are once the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of his almighty hands, then will he make them ſtrong, and fertile, <hi>a little one ſhall become a thouſand,</hi> and <hi>a ſmall one a ſtrong nation, Iſa.</hi> 60.22. In a word, the leaſt meaſure of Grace, being the work of the Holy Spirit of God, is therefore call'd [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>a new creation,</hi> or a new creature, and be ſure none ſhall be abortive, which he begets, but go on to be an Heir of Glory, and Chriſt calls this child of the Spirit by his own name, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. <hi>My little children, of whom I travel in birth again 'till Chriſt be formed in you.</hi> This clearly ſignifies to us, that he will be as careful, and tender, of this Divine nature, this piece of himſelf, as if it were himſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth reaſon is, becauſe the leaſt meaſure of Grace differs only gradually from the greateſt meaſure, they are the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110142:13"/>
ſame in kind, and nature; as the leaſt drop of water is water, and the leaſt ſpark of fire is fire; therefore Chriſt's care, and love, is not reſtrain'd to the degree of Grace, but extends to the whole ſpecies of new creatures, ſmall, and great, weak, and ſtrong, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. The Apoſtle writes to them, that had obtain'd like <hi>pretious faith with us</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] it was not equal in degree with his, but, being of the ſame nature, and kind, it was of equal price, and value, with God; and therefore Chriſt will (being exceeding careful to) keep this heavenly treaſure: Little Grace is a little grain of muſtard-ſeed, which grows, and ſpreads into a great tree, and it is compar'd ſo for it's ſmallneſs at firſt, as well as for it's growth at laſt. And, if thou haſt but the leaſt Grace, I dare tell thee, that God hath done more for thee in that, than if he ſhould in making that, which is now ſo weak, as perfect, as the Saint's Grace is now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and that for two reaſons. 1. Becauſe it was an act of greater power to work Grace out of no Grace than to add that Grace by perfectional Grace. There is a greater gulf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween no Grace, and Grace, than between weak Grace, and ſtrong; between a Chaos, and nothing, than between a Chaos, and the beautiful frame of this World. The firſt day's work of both creations is the greateſt, and therefore God will by no means <hi>deſpiſe the day of theſe ſmall things,</hi> which, as inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as we think them to be, are the effect of the ſame almighty power, as created the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is an act of greater mercy to give us the firſt Grace in converſion, than to crown that Grace with Glory; it is a greater favour, and condeſcenſion, in a Prince to marry a poor damſel, than, having married her, to cloth her like a Princeſs; he was free to do, or not to do, the former, but now his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her obliges him to do the latter; even ſo might God have choſen whether he would have given thee Grace or not at the firſt, but, having done this, thy relation to him, and his covenant alſo, do oblige him to preſerve that Grace, and add more 'till he hath fitted thee, as a bride, for himſelf in Glory, therefore let the weakeſt Chriſtian never doubt of Criſt's care, and tenderneſs, towards him, for he, that hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110142:13"/>
done the greater acts of power, and mercy, to him, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do the leſſer; he, that gave him ſpiritual life equal to the beſt Saint in Heaven in quality, and nature, will ſurely give it nouriſhment, and growth, 'till it comes to perfection, or, as it is in my Text, <hi>'till he bring forth judgement unto victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The covenant of Grace comprehends the weak, as well as the ſtrong, Chriſtian, <hi>If children, then heirs, heirs of God, and co-heirs with Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.17. The promiſe there is not to children grown to this, or that, ſtrength, or ſtature, if thou beeſt a child, tho' in the cradle, the promiſes are thy portion, yea thou may'ſt plead for his care, and maintenance, 'till thou poſſeſs the inheritance in Heaven, upon thy ſtate, and relation, and not upon thy weaker, or ſtronger, Grace. Some Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have more Grace from Chriſt, than others, and ſo have more skill to improve theſe promiſes, than their weaker Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whereby their preſent profits, and incomes, from the promiſes are greater; but they have no more intereſt in Chriſt, than the other, and conſequently the weak Chriſtian's title is as true to the promiſe, as that of the ſtrong: tho' the foot is the loweſt member of the body, yet it cannot ſay, but that the tongue will ſpeak for it, and the head take care of it, for the foot is in the body; and ſo is the meaneſt Believer in the body of Chriſt; therefore thoſe do disfigure the promiſes, that make them look aſquint, with an eye upon one Believer, and not upon another; whereas they equally belong to all; <hi>He, that believes on the Son, hath everlaſting life, Jo.</hi> 3.36. and who is meant there? is it he, that believes above doubting? ſurely no, but we may be aſſur'd of this, that he, that commands us to <hi>receive the weak in faith,</hi> will not himſelf reject them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Grace may be weak in one reſpect, and yet ſtrong in another; a Chriſtian may be weak in his active, and ſtrong, and reſolute, in his paſſive, obedience; <hi>Rahab</hi>'s Faith was but <hi>a grain of muſtard ſeed,</hi> yet it was of the right kind, becauſe ſhe held out a profeſſor in <hi>Jericho;</hi> her godly courage, and hope, were ſtrong in the Lord, elſe ſhe had never continu'd her obedience to the true God among ſuch a number of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110142:14"/>
A Believer may be wanting in his zeal, and activity, in God's ſervice, and reſiſting temptations, in maſtering corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, yet, as a tree in winter, he grows downward in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſelf-abhorrence, and his whole dependance is upon God through Chriſt, in the ſenſe of his wants, and ſo, being deeply rooted in theſe, the Lord will ſooner diſpenſe with his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward infirmities.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The number of weak Believers is far greater, than that of the ſtrong, and therefore, if Chriſt takes not ſpecial care to carry his lambs in his boſom, his fold is like to be very empty. There are more ſparrows, than Eagles, more bruiſed reeds, than Cedars, and more babes in Chriſt, than ſtrong, well grown, Chriſtians in God's Family, therefore, if he were not a very tender nurſing Father to theſe, thoſe eternal manſions of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould be like to want inhabitants.</p>
            <p n="8">8, and laſtly, Hereby God ſheweth his ſtrength, and power, and ſo more Glory redounds to Chriſt, by this care in keeping alive a ſparkle of Grace in an ocean of corruption, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>My ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſs,</hi> that is, not intrinſecally, but declaratively, not made ſo, but manifeſted to the Sons of Men to be ſo. This cuts the very comb of pride in all, and leaves no room for ſelf-exaltation, when God is both the founder, and finiſher of their Grace. And that, which highly advanceth his Glory, is, that he alone holdeth, as our Souls, ſo our Grace, in life. This not only magnifies, but omnifies, his power, and cauſeth the poor Chriſtian to lay the crown of all his ſervices upon the head of Chriſt, and to cry out with St. <hi>Paul, It is not I, but the grace of God, which was with me;</hi> and when all is done, and the race is run in glory, <hi>to caſt his crown with the elders before the throne</hi> of Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, honour, and power,</hi> Rev. 4.10, 11. Having thus done with the reaſons, I ſhall anſwer an objection that meets me in my way, which is this, If Chriſt be ſo tender of them, why are they ſo full of fears, and doubts, and hard thoughts of themſelves, touching their ſpiritual, and eternal condition, as uſually they are?</p>
            <p n="1">1. I anſwer, It is by reaſon of their ignorance of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110142:14"/>
of Grace, and their miſtakes about the exerciſes, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Grace, eſpecially by reaſon of the motes in their eyes of Faith; they think they have no Faith, becauſe they want the <hi>aſsurance of faith,</hi> (which the Apoſtle calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which is not of the eſſence of Faith, but a conſequent of it, and a reflex act of the Soul upon it ſelf attain'd by a long continu'd courſe of holy, and cloſe, walking with God, which few Believers have: but Faith is a recumbant act of the Soul upon Chriſt, and is uſually expreſs'd by the inſtance of one, that, having ſuffer'd ſhipwrack, caſt himſelf upon a floating plank of the ſhip, and there ſticks in a trembling, doubtfull hope of coming aſhore.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt Grace <hi>in ideâ,</hi> and Grace <hi>in ſubjecto, in actu ſignato,</hi> and <hi>in actu exercito;</hi> as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The wonderfull operations of Charity are deſcrib'd there, now, becauſe weak Chriſtians can find no ſuch effects in themſelves, they preſently conclude themſelves to be no better, than <hi>ſounding braſs,</hi> and <hi>tinkling cymbals,</hi> meer empty nothings, and no real Chriſtians; but they ought to diſtinguiſh betwixt this Grace in it's own abſtracted nature, and as it is in the ſubject mixt with the fleſh, and contrary elements of corruptions, and ſo it is not ſo operative in the beſt of Chriſtians, as being obſtructed by it's contrary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Fire by it ſelf is viſible, and active, but not ſo in the flint, and yet we know it is there, tho' conceal'd under the other elements: ſo we may judge of Charity, and other Graces with the mixtures of contrary imperfections, which do retard, and make them come ſhort of their genuine productions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is becauſe they compare themſelves with the uppermoſt in Chriſt's ſchool for proficiency, and, becauſe they are not ſuch glorious lights in the firmament of the Church, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> and other Scripture Saints, therefore, in their own opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, they are but Meteors, and wandring Stars, Hypocrites, and Unbelievers. But they ſhould know that, as it is in the Kingdom of Glory, ſo it is in the Kingdom of Grace, <hi>one ſtar differeth from another,</hi> and the members of the body myſtical, as in the body natural, are not of equal ſtrength, and bigneſs:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110142:15"/>
All Chriſtians ſhould therefore labour to be of the body of Chriſt, and not be diſcouraged, though they be but the meaneſt finger, or the loweſt toe, for their head will be ſure to take care of them, and bring them at laſt to himſelf. We muſt be ſure to get the ſame Grace, as others, for truth, though we cannot attain to the ſame grace for meaſure, we muſt try our ſelves by the ſame touch-ſtone, tho' not weigh our ſelves in the ſame ballance, we muſt be of the ſame mettal as others, though not of the ſame weight.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe they examine themſelves in an unſeaſonable time, when overcome with ſadneſs, and black melancholick thoughts: then indeed they are to ſeek for the leaſt Grace: But we muſt conſider that, though this ſelf-examination is neceſſary, yet it is not at all times to be uſed.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly diſpatch'd what I at firſt propoſed to ſpeak to, I come now in the laſt place to apply the whole.</p>
            <p>This truth concerns four ſorts of people, 1. The Miniſters of the Goſpel. 2. Strong Chriſtians. 3. Weak Chriſtians. 4. Such as are <hi>aliens from the common-wealth of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Miniſters <hi>ſhould have the ſame mind in them, as was in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> when they ſee a <hi>bruiſed reed,</hi> to ſupport it, and carry on the work of Grace in Chriſtian hearts; we muſt encourage the weak hearted, and ſtrengthen feeble knees, for we are the immediate ſubordinate, outward, agents to do this work for Chriſt, and to fulfill this promiſe of his. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> calls St. <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] the WALL of the people, and ſo ſhould we be an impregnable wall about our people for to defend them (eſpecially at this time of Apoſtacy) from Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and falſe teachers. There are <hi>wolves in ſheep's clothing,</hi> that will ſoon make a havock of Chriſt's lambs, that will, by their Sophiſtry, ſeduce young Chriſtians, unleſs we fortify them not only by our conſtant preaching of the truth in publick, but alſo by our perſonal application of that truth to them in private.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Strong Chriſtians ſhould make it appear that they are ſo by ſerving the Lord Chriſt in this work, and labour of love, by taking their weak brethren by the hand, and helping them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110142:15"/>
out of the mire of temptations: you know whoſe language it was, <hi>Am I my brother's keeper?</hi> a curſed <hi>Cain</hi>'s: be you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bleſſed in incouraging the feeble, inſtructing the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and confirming the doubtful; comfort weak Believers againſt the violence of the perſecutor, arm them againſt the Sophiſtry of the Seducer, and, by your exemplary lives teach them to mortify the fleſh, to bridle the tongue, to adorn their profeſſion with a holy converſation, and to prepare themſelves againſt approaching miſeries. In all your ſtations, and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do all the good you can for YOUR LORD'S, and MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER'S, ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is a word to weak Chriſtians, here is a cordial for them to reſtore their fainting Spirits, when ſurpriz'd with any fears touching their perſevering to the end of their warfare.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be of good comfort, <hi>thy life</hi> ſpiritual, and eternal, <hi>is hid with Chriſt in God;</hi> ſay not, thou art a <hi>bruiſed reed,</hi> for with this will Chriſt <hi>break Satan's head,</hi> and he will not ceaſe <hi>'till he hath brought forth Judgement unto</hi> compleat <hi>Victory</hi> in thy Soul. All the power, and malice, of Hell ſhall not be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the leaſt ſpark of Grace in any Soul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Take the cup</hi> of thankſgiving <hi>and call on the name of the Lord,</hi> bleſs God, whilſt thou liveſt, for thy new creation, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; take up <hi>David</hi>'s language, <hi>My ſoul, praiſe thou the Lord, all, that is within me, bleſs his holy name, what ſhall I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Lord for all his</hi> care, and kindneſs, his preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and providence? Alas! how ſoon had <hi>Satan winnowed</hi> me, if the Lord had not prayed for me, and upheld me? his almighty arm ſupported me, elſe I had, long ago, inevitably dropt into <hi>everlaſting burning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Love</hi> him <hi>with all your heart, with all your ſoul;</hi> all this care, and tenderneſs towards you is the fruit of his love; Oh! then let love in him beget the like love in you, beget an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire <hi>to run the ways of his commandments</hi> with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; Oh! pant, and breath, after him, and reſt no where, but in the boſom of his love.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be you tender of him, and careful to pleaſe him, as the Spouſe was, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6, 7. ſhe was weak in knowledge, and in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110142:16"/>
Grace, and therefore Chriſt's <hi>left hand is under her head, and his right hand embraceth her;</hi> then ſhe chargeth her ſelf in her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular members not to diſturb him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take heed you <hi>quench not this ſmoking flax,</hi> your ſelves, which is done, Firſt, by negligence, and careleſsneſs in God's ſervice, we muſt [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>ſtir up</hi> the Grace of God, that is in us, or elſe it will dy of it ſelf, if we do not blow this fire into a flame it will quench unknown to us. Secondly, By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to folly again, this is the water, that quencheth the ſparkle of Grace, and is abominable to God, and therefore compared by him to the <hi>vomiting of a dog,</hi> and to the <hi>wallowing of a ſow in the mire.</hi> Thirdly, By accompanying wicked Men, which are as <hi>floods of waters,</hi> and <hi>waves of the ſea,</hi> to quench this ſparkle, and ſo term'd by the Prophet <hi>David</hi> in ſeveral Pſalms; therefore avoid them, as you would avoid the Devil, for they are his inſtruments.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth uſe is to ſtrangers from the covenant of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that they would conſider what a bleſſed condition it is to have Chriſt for a guardian, and how happy are the people, that are under his tuition; 'tis impoſſible to conceive how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully careful, and tender, he is of the weakeſt Believer; the relations of a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> a <hi>father,</hi> of a <hi>mother, Husband,</hi> &amp;c. do prove it, and preach it. Oh! then let all be hence incited to take him upon his own terms, that they may be under his care, and tenderneſs, that he may keep you in all your ways: defer not therefore to cloſe with him, that you may be thus, and eternally, happy.</p>
            <q>Now to God the Father, God the Son, God the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, praiſe, and dominion, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110142:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
